本期Primal Space视频由Audible赞助
This episode of Primal Space is supported by Audible.
前往视频中链接可获取一本免费的有声书 外加30天的Audible试用
Get a free audio book plus a 30-day free trial by visiting the link below.
1919年 飞行员Alcock和Brown
In the year 1919, pilots Alcock and Brown
驾驶飞机从加拿大飞往爱尔兰 完成了人类首次跨大西洋飞行
completed the first non-stop transatlantic flight from Canada to Ireland.
这趟旅程只花了他们16小时 但远没有想象的一帆风顺
The journey took them just 16 hours, but it was anything but plain sailing.
起飞时 超载的飞机几乎擦着一排树梢飞过
During takeoff, the overloaded aircraft barely made it over a line of trees.
过了不久 机载发电机坏了 导致他们没法用通信和加热设备
And shortly after, the onboard generator failed, causing them to lose radio contact and their heating system.
更惨的是 飞行员之后还遇到了突发的浓雾
The pilots faced even more trouble when they were suddenly surrounded by a thick layer of fog.
他们当时利用六分仪观星导航 浓雾让他们彻底迷失了方向
Since they were using the stars to navigate, they became completely lost.
低能见度又让Alcock发生空间迷向 螺旋俯冲后差点摔海里
And the lack of visibility caused Alcock to lose control of the aircraft, narrowly missing the sea.
在经历了暴风雪和在爱尔兰轻微的摔机着陆后 飞行员们终于成功横跨了大西洋
One snow storm later and a minor crash landing in Ireland, the pilots made it across the Atlantic.
这次伟大成就最终成为了人类航空旅行的开端
This major accomplishment ultimately led to the beginning of passenger air travel.
但Alcock和Brown的极其艰难的旅程恰恰体现了飞行员职责的重要性
But Alcock and Brown's incredibly rough journey showed just how essential the role of the pilot was.
40年后 在人类航天的起步阶段
40 years later and with spaceflight just around the corner,
NASA启动了X-15计划 来探究人类与航天器如何应对太空飞行
NASA set up the X-15 program to determine how humans and aircraft would cope with flights into space.
X-15是一款以火箭为动力的飞机
The X-15 was a rocket-powered aircraft,
飞行高度可达100km 速度可达7000km/h
capable of reaching altitudes above 100km and speeds of 7,000km/h
该计划的主要目标是探究人类在太空飞行中的极限
One of the main goals of the program was to explore the limitations of humans in spaceflight
——找出哪些是人类擅长的 哪些是计算机擅长的
—find out what humans are better at and what computers are better at.
经历了9年 199次飞行后 NASA发现 人类虽然能驾驶火箭进入太空
After 9 years and 199 flights, NASA found that while a human could fly a rocket into space,
但自动系统却能完成相同的任务且精度更高
the automated system could perform the same task with much more accuracy.
随着NASA把重心放在了火箭上
Once NASA switched their attention to rockets,
人类在火箭上的职责也开始明确——不是驾驶火箭 而是监督火箭
it was clear that the role of the human would not be to fly the rocket, but to monitor what it was doing.
虽然飞机可以仅由两名飞行员驾驶
While an airplane can be flown with just a couple of pilots,
但火箭却需要一个完整的团队在任务控制中心持续监看火箭的每一部分
a rocket takes a whole team of people back at mission control, to constantly monitor each part of the rocket.
到了今天 火箭的发射已经完全自动化
To this day, rocket launches are completely automated.
以重型猎鹰火箭为例
Take the Falcon Heavy for example.
发射前60秒 火箭箭载计算机接管飞行控制
60 seconds before launch, the rockets onboard computers take control of the flight.
从这一刻开始 火箭的这些操作 全靠它自己！
And from then on, the rocket does this, all by itself!
如果火箭都能做到 那为什么民航飞机不能没有飞行员呢？
If a rocket can do this, then why can't an airliner fly without a pilot?
虽然现代民航飞机有很完善的自动驾驶系统
Although modern airliners have very capable autopilot systems,
但主要功能是减少飞行员的工作量 而不是驾驶飞机
their main job is to reduce the workload for the pilot and not to fly the plane.
而这也不代表飞机全自动飞行是不可能的
However, this doesn't mean it's impossible for an aircraft to fly itself.
回到1947年 美国空军进行了一次飞行试验
Back in 1947, the US Air Force performed an experimental flight
使用C-54"空中霸王"飞机从加拿大飞往英国
from Canada to England using a C-54 Skymaster.
飞行员将载有7名成员的飞机滑行到跑道上
With a seven-man crew onboard, the pilot taxied onto the runway,
按下了自动驾驶接通按钮 将控制权交给了飞机
let go of the controls and pushed a button to engage the autopilot.
飞机自己完成了起飞
The plane took off by itself,
自动调整了襟翼和油门 离地后自动收回了起落架
automatically adjusting its flaps and throttles and, once airborne, retracting its landing gear.
随后按照事先编写好的程序 飞机自己按照一系列流程横跨了大西洋
It then flew itself across the Atlantic,
following a series of sequences that had been programmed into its "mechanical brain".
在第二天黎明时分 C-53抵达了英国的海岸 并进行了一次完美的着陆
At dawn the following day, the C-54 reach the English coast and executed a perfect landing.
短暂的恰饭
以上节选自Nicholas Carr的有声书"The Glass Cage"
This was a sample from an audiobook called "The Glass Cage" by Nicholas Carr.
这是一本展望自动化未来的有声书
It's an audiobook that looks at the future of automation.
探索了机器人、自动驾驶汽车、数字化医疗等领域
Exploring things like robots, self-driving cars, and digitized medicine.
这本书和很多其他书都在Audible上有有声书的版本
This book along with many others, is available as an audiobook on Audible,
可以让你随时随地去听
so you can listen to it on the go, no matter where you are.
前往视频中链接即可免费获得一本有声书
On top of that, you can get your first audiobook,
Audible的30天试用和两份Audible Originals
a 30 day trial and two Audible Originals all for free
by visiting Audible.com/PrimalSpace or texting Primal Space to 500 500.
以今天的技术 飞机全自动起飞着陆是完全可能的
With today's technology, an aircraft capable of taking off and landing all by itself is definitely possible.
但让全自动的飞机像飞行员那样安全地处理各种无法预料的情景还很困难
But getting a fully automated aircraft to deal with every unexpected scenario
whilst still being as safe as a pilot is way more difficult.
更不用提如今民航基建如此完善
Not to mention that our airline infrastructure is so developed,
想要完全把飞行员替换下去
that in order to replace the pilot completely,
飞机还要能自动在停机位与跑道之间滑行
each airplane would need to be able to taxi between the gate and the runway,
全程需要保持和机场其他飞机的通信
all whilst communicating with every other plane at the airport.
说白了 如果波音明天出了一款全新的无飞行员的飞机 那FAA肯定懵逼了
To put it simply, if Boeing came out tomorrow with their new pilotless airliner, the FAA would lose their minds.
节选自1980年喜剧电影《空前绝后满天飞》
额滴娘啊 自动飞行员漏气了！
Oh my God! The automatic pilot, it's deflating!
而航天飞行从一开始 火箭就一直是靠自己的制导系统
Since the beginning of spaceflight, rockets have always operated under their own guidance systems.
应付如此高空高速的情况
When dealing with such high speeds and altitudes,
计算机控制的火箭能比任何人类控制的入轨更加精确
computers are able to guide the rocket into orbit with much more precision than a human ever could.
自动化系统用在猎鹰九号的着陆上则有更加明显的优势
The advantage that automated systems provide is even more clear when we look at the landing of the Falcon 9.
因为火箭着陆时推重比始终大于1
Since the rocket has a thrust to weight ratio higher than 1 during a landing,
使得它必须执行一次"suicide burn"
it has to perform a "suicide burn"
即在最后某一刻让发动机点火
which involves firing the engines at the last possible second.
发动机开早了 火箭会在还没到地面的时候就停下来
Turn on the engines too soon and the rocket will slow down before reaching the ground.
发动机开晚了 火箭又没有足够时间减速
Turn on the engines too late and the rocket won't be able to slow down in time.
在火箭着陆时 其计算机会根据其高度和速度
As the rocket comes in, its onboard computers are constantly measuring its altitude and its speed,
实时解算发动机点火时间
to work out when to light the engines.
在完美的时间点火
Getting the timing absolutely perfect
成功的同学会看到彩蛋哦~
就好比在倒计时刚好到0.00的时候暂停这个视频一样
is like trying to pause this video when the number reaches zero.
人类是几乎做不到的
You can't.
虽然猎鹰九号可以以惊人的精度着陆
Although the Falcon 9 is able to land with incredible accuracy,
但这高度依赖GPS的精确定位来预测落点
it relies largely on GPS to precisely guide it to a predetermined landing spot.
这在未来火星任务中是无法做到的
This is something that won't be possible for future missions to Mars,
因为目前火星上没有GPS支持其完成定点精确着陆
since there is no current GPS system around the planet to provide pinpoint accuracy.
到了2022年 太空叉打算使用新的Starship火箭执行火星货运任务
In 2022, SpaceX plans to send a cargo mission to Mars using their new Starship rocket.
在未来 太空叉有可能会在火星表面建设着陆场
In the future, it's possible that SpaceX could build landing pads on the Martian surface
并为火星GPS发射卫星星座
and operate a constellation of satellites to give Mars its own GPS.
但在最初几次任务中 Starship需要能够自行实时分析地形
But for the first couple of missions, Starship will need to analyze the terrain in real time
选择一个合适的着陆点
and choose a suitable landing spot all by itself.
这就是少有的 人类比计算机更有用的场景之一
This is one of the few situations where human input is more valuable than a computer.
在阿波罗11号着陆过程中
During the landing of Apollo 11,
机载计算机引导登月舱飞往一块充满巨石的区域
the onboard computers were taking the Lunar Module towards a field of boulders.
因为计算机没有意识到潜在的危险
Since the computers were unaware of the possible danger,
尼尔·阿姆斯特朗接管了登月舱的控制 引导其着陆在一块更平整的月面上
Neil Armstrong had to take control of the Lunar Module and direct it towards a clear patch of ground.
对于Starship着陆火星来说 它可能会有自己的人工智能视角
For Starship landing on Mars, it could have its own artificial vision,
利用多个训练后的箭载相机避开复杂地形 让飞船着陆在平整的火星表面
with multiple onboard cameras trained to avoid rough terrain and land the spacecraft on flat ground.
另一个建议解决方案是在着陆区附近事先放下几个小型应答机
Another solution that many have suggested is to land a series of small transponders near the landing site
创造一个局部的导航系统
to create a localised GPS.
保证其中至少三个能和Starship通信
At least three of these would be able to communicate with Starship and accurately plot its position,
引导其在着陆场精确着陆
guiding it towards the landing site.
无论哪种方法 Starship的首次火星着陆都将是一次极为困难且令人兴奋的事件
Either way, the first Starship landing on Mars will be an incredibly tense but exciting event!
另一个令人兴奋的事情是Audible提供的海量的有声书
Another thing that's exciting is the incredible range of audio books that Audible has to offer.
Audible有独一无二的 各种能想象到的领域的有声书
Audible has an unmatched selection of audio books covering every topic imaginable.
他们甚至还有关于X-15计划的有声书 里面有参与此计划的先驱的访谈
They even have an audio book all about the X-15 program with interviews from the pioneers that made it happen.
前往上方链接可以获取Audible的30天免费试用
Start listening today with a 30-day free trial
by visiting audible.com/primalspace or texting 'primalspace' to 500-500
感谢观看 我们下期视频见
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video.